The layoffs continue, and
some are pretty… malicious.
Oracle is targeting workers with unvested stock,
CEOs are calling cut staff “low
performers” even when they aren’t.
Staff get layoff emails at 4am.
It’s all so weird.
And now, it seems to be backfiring.
In some cases, very drastically.
Doesn’t it feel like something’s
broken in corporate culture?
It feels like that unspoken contract, and
trust between staff and company, is breaking.
This is what happens when your
employees start to hate you.
We’re in a strange time right now.
All these layoffs aren’t because companies
are struggling, it’s actually the opposite.
“While AI leaders insist that their
tools will empower and augment workers
instead of displacing them, several
companies, especially those in tech,
have initiated mass layoffs and are
prioritizing spending on AI above workers.”
These companies are making more profit than ever,
and this stage of layoffs is about companies
“consolidating” or focusing on “efficiency”.
And as we’ll see, that’s not entirely true…
Cloudflare generated $639.8 million in
just the first three months of 2026,
a 34% increase from the previous year.
Two months later, on May 7, Cloudflare
laid off 1,000 employees to rely
more on AI. About 20% of the company.
Some who were fired weren’t even given a reason.
IBM's CEO Krishna promised more grad
hiring, then laid off thousands days later.
Several CEOs have even attended graduation
ceremonies to give speeches promoting AI,
including current and former Google
CEOs Sundar Pichai and Eric Schmidt.
And there’s more,
Pinterest announced cutting 15%
of staff to invest in AI, out of 4,700 employees.
Atlassian laid off 1,600 people, called it an "AI
investment," and its stock rose about 2%.
Intel’s also restructuring and eliminating
more than 25,000 positions, about
1/5 of their entire headcount.
But one of the strangest is Meta.
First, theirs was amongst the
biggest layoffs. 8,000 in May 2026.
This was also, out of nowhere. Employees
woke up to termination emails sent at 4am.
‘Yesterday I was training up my new pod
engineer, glad I managed to squeeze
in everything. Today. I'm laid off,’
And to make matters worse,
leaked audio reveals more.
Not great.
More than 1,000
employees signed an internal petition demanding
the company stop using that data for AI training.
But, things are a bit more nuanced.
Regarding those layoffs, Meta is
offering pretty generous severance packages and
healthcare support, better than most tech layoffs.
They’ve also reassigned more than 7,000 workers to
new teams centred around artificial intelligence,
instead of cutting them.
But some of these get much worse.
Before we get to that, I’d like to talk
to you about today’s sponsor ZocDoc.
These layoffs are especially tough for those who
may have moved cities or even states for this job.
I myself recently moved across the
country, and one of the most difficult
challenges is finding a new doctor.
You have to navigate all the options,
figure out which are good, which
are covered by your insurance,
and when you finally find the right one…
Sorry! No spots available for three weeks!
It’s so confusing and overwhelming,
but it doesn’t have to be.
ZocDoc is a free platform that
lets you search and compare local,
in-network doctors. Over 150,000 providers
within 200+ specialties, across all 50 states.
One of the most important factors in our
health is information. That’s why we’re
told to get checked often, so we can
catch a disease early, and treat it.
Zocdoc equips you with all you need.
See if patients rate the doctor,
see which network they’re in and
if they’re covered by insurance.
You can even see a doctor’s schedule,
and when they’re available! Appointments are
usually within 24-72 hours, and you can even
book same-day appointments.
No need to wait weeks,
to get answers you need within days.
ZocDoc isn’t a healthcare provider.
They help you cut through the noise,
and make healthcare less overwhelming.
ZocDoc believes the healthcare
industry should work for patients.
Life is already difficult
enough. Give ZocDoc a try,
it’s totally free. You might see a better
doctor in your city who’s free this week.
Click the link in the description, or scan the
QR code on screen, get instant access to 150,000
providers, and make more informed decisions.
Thank you to ZocDoc for sponsoring this video.
There is Oracle, this year it laid off 21,000
workers to build its business around AI.
They estimate that a layoff this large
could free up $8 billion to $10 billion
for AI infrastructure spending.
But, Oracle is particularly painful.
Some employees had their bonuses tied to
unvested restricted stock, which was now gone.
One former software manager lost nearly $1
million in unvested stock that he was set
to get in just four months, despite
it making up 70% of his total pay.
A technical writer also lost a $300,000
bonus tied to unvested restricted stock.
It sure seemed like Oracle
was targeting these layoffs
at people with outstanding stock.
As a 30-year Oracle veteran said
“It seems (BUT I DON’T KNOW), maybe,
layoffs follow an algorithm of high level
individual contributors and mid-level managers –
especially those with outstanding stock options,”
For context, Oracle just reported its best growth
quarter in 15 years, now with a market cap over
$400 billion. Though, Oracle is experiencing
some pretty big problems with its AI plans,
as we’ll find out soon.
But in the meantime,
workers are having a rough time.
Some ex-staff were in the U.S. on
H-1B visas and now had just 60 days to
find another job or leave the country.
Many of the layoffs are those over
40 years old, and 22% are those who
worked at Oracle for over 15 years.
Workers demanded Oracle match the more
generous severance packages offered by Meta,
Microsoft, and Cloudflare, including longer
pay and accelerated stock vesting.
Yeah, Oracle didn’t do that.
But there wasn't much employees could do about it.
Oracle employees aren't unionised.
In April, more than 600 Oracle employees signed a
letter to company management asking for increased
severance, extended health care, and other
benefits. Oracle responded by saying that it
will only address concerns individually.
Not only that,
“The company has since been rejecting many
individual requests for better severance,
sometimes responding with cookie-cutter
language that has nothing to do with
the individual’s circumstances,”.
Oh, Oracle workers were training the
AI that replaced them, by the way.
The job cuts were painful,
but what made them particularly bad was how these
executives chose to… justify?... or label them?
The founder of Oracle, Larry Ellison,
bragged at an Oracle development conference:
But in reality, former employees had to spend
time trying to reverse-engineer faulty code that
juniors had generated due to Oracle’s AI mandates.
Ellison also said:
"We are choosing the chips. Anyone whose job is
not making the chips run faster... is at risk."
Workers are basically training
an AI clone of themselves.
"They're having you do something, it's recorded,
and then they're going to replace
you with whatever you just built."
Some CEOs justify job cuts by
undermining the people they just fired.
Zuckerberg described the layoffs
as removing “low performers.”
Pretty awful thing to be labelled when trying
to find new work, especially when many of
these employees weren’t low performers
at all, according to internal reviews.
Cloudflare CEO Matthew Prince also sorted
staff into "measurers" vs builders and
wrote that "the vast majority of those
we laid off last week were measurers".
“The way these layoffs have been handled,
it feels like a clear signal that humans
are treated like another asset. Just like
data center assets that can be disposed of
if they’re not the most profitable option.”
But, some of these layoffs are backfiring.
When things are done in such bad faith,
there can often be large blowback.
These layoffs are pretty depressing, but,
we’ve gotten some pretty funny responses from
staff. Those cut, and even those who weren’t.
After announcing layoffs, two engineers at
Pinterest built a tool to track internal
job cuts after the company refused
to share information identifying
impacted employees. They were quickly fired.
The CEO told workers at a company-wide meeting
“they should consider working elsewhere if they
are working against the direction of the company,”
We're seeing a shift in corporate culture,
and things only get more dramatic from here.
Workers' loyalty to their companies is
essentially gone. But loyalty to fellow
workers and co-workers is growing stronger.
A perfect example is Vasilios Syrakis,
who was laid off in March 2026, after spending
more than eight years as a senior systems engineer
working on Atlassian's edge infrastructure.
He was part of the company's more than 1,600
layoffs as it redirected spending towards AI.
So he released a video.
Within just eight days,
this video had passed 1 million views.
It currently sits at over 2.3 million.
“This has to be the most badass thing
ever to happen in the IT world this year”
“Build infrastructure for company
to grow to nearly $25 billion market
cap ($1.79 billion in revenue last
quarter). Gets laid off. Gives away
Atlassian's entire infrastructure
for free online for anyone to copy.”
He’s perfectly within his rights to do this, by
the way. Most of it was publicly available on
Atlassian's engineering blog.
Videos like this are now
popping up all over YouTube.
But some videos are a bit different.
This is David Frenk, who was laid
off. He made this American Pie
parody for other Meta employees,
which then leaked outside of Meta.
Also, remember the weird letter
from the Cloudflare CEO? Well…
This is Chamath Palihapitiya, venture
capitalist and former Facebook executive.
He’s totally right though.
I think these executives are
scared to be honest about why they’re doing
these layoffs, which is basically putting
it back into AI spend, so they come up with
terms like “measurers”, or “low performers”.
I don’t know if layoffs will stop, but
it does seem like CEOs are realising just
laying everyone off isn’t helping a ton.
Zuckerberg has also admitted that he made
mistakes with some of these layoffs.
Now Meta is trying to win workers back.
The company plans to increase spending
on offsites and corporate events,
including a company-wide hackathon in July.
And all of this is happening while Meta
raises its annual spending forecast
from $125 billion to $145 billion.
I think he knows what these
layoffs have cost them.
Not just in capital but in trust.
Ford is also re-hiring 300 veteran
quality inspectors, after the AI that replaced
them… didn’t really live up to expectations.
Who could’ve seen that coming.
[Charles Poon, vice president
of vehicle hardware engineering, Ford]:
“Over prior years, we didn't pay as much
attention as we should have to the experience
of our most knowledgeable engineers that have
been with us through many product cycles”
Wish more executives would admit this fact.
But, not everyone is interested in reconciliation.
Some workers have chosen a very different
response: revenge. Even to the point of
sabotaging their own careers.
And this is only increasing.
According to a Fortune survey, 29% of
employees admitted to sabotaging their
company's AI strategy. Among Gen Z
workers, that figure jumps to 44%.
Some engage in what is known as data poisoning,
deliberately feeding AI systems bad, misleading,
or proprietary information
to contaminate the output.
Others manipulate performance metrics, making
it appear that AI tools are performing worse
than they actually are. Roughly one in
ten workers admit to doing exactly that.
Some bypass the company AI system to feed
their company data to other AI platforms.
Then there is what some call generating garbage.
Workers intentionally prompt AI systems to produce
low-quality, nonsensical, or unusable results,
creating the impression that the technology
is unreliable or simply not ready for the job.
There is a growing tension
between employers and employees.
And as companies push deeper into
AI, trust appears to be collapsing.
A Yahoo survey found that 67% of respondents
believed their company had already suffered
a data leak or security breach because
an employee used an unapproved AI tool.
At the same time, 76% of executives
said employee sabotage poses a
serious threat to their company's future.
And perhaps the reason isn't hard to find.
In the same survey, 60% of companies said they
plan to lay off workers who refuse to adopt AI.
Think about the dynamic that creates.
Use AI, or get laid off. And even if you do,
you might still get laid off. Doesn't
make you feel great no matter what you do.
How can you work in an environment like this?
So many are trying to “poison” the
AI that’s replacing them.
Several AI-industry insiders
launched a project called Poison Fountain.
Its goal is simple: convincing website
operators to embed poisoned information
designed specifically for AI crawlers.
Another survey of 1,000 employees and
178 managers found that 85% of recently
laid-off workers attempted some form of
retaliation against their former employer.
Remote workers were 47% more likely
to do so than on-site employees.
The most common methods were surprisingly simple:
posting inappropriate content on company social
media accounts, sending inappropriate emails
to clients, and stealing company assets.
Meanwhile, DTEX's Insider Risk report
found a 35% increase in data theft by
departing employees during layoff events.
That was back in 2023 and it’s likely
much higher now, and we’re seeing it,
especially in some very extreme cases.
Tech companies are increasingly finding
themselves in legal battles with former employees.
After Intel announced more than 35,000 job
cuts over two years, the company accused Luo,
a software engineer of 11 years, of copying
sensitive company files before disappearing.
According to Intel, he spent four
days transferring more than 18,000
documents, some marked "Intel Top
Secret," onto an external drive.
Then, he was gone.
We don’t condone
this… of course… but that’s pretty funny.
Intel’s spent more than three months trying
to contact him through phone calls,
emails, and even physical letters.
The company is now suing for $250,000
and demanding the return of the data.
His whereabouts remain unknown.
And Intel isn't alone.
Elon Musk's xAI has also gone after
a former engineer, Xuechen Li.
Allegedly, Li took confidential information,
including uploading xAI's entire codebase,
before moving to OpenAI.
A judge temporarily blocked
him from working on or discussing AI technology
with OpenAI while the case moved through court.
According to xAI, this wasn't just
one employee taking information.
The company claims OpenAI was actively recruiting
workers with access to Grok's source code.
It feels like something’s broken right now.
Socially, that is.
Workers gave companies their time, loyalty,
expertise, and sometimes entire careers.
In return, companies offered
stability, opportunity,
career growth, and the promise that if
you performed well, you’d be rewarded.
This was the social, unspoken
contract. It goes both ways.
But doesn’t it feel like that
unspoken trust is breaking?
Oracle clawed back stock that employees
had spent years working toward.
Meta pushed out workers while branding
many of them as "low performers."
Cloudflare calling staff "measurers."
4am layoff emails,
years of loyalty erased overnight.
Why work here, if there’s no mutual benefit?
I think it’s why people are spending
less time with companies. Because, well,
they don’t take care of them like they used to.
A company has moved away from a group of
people who agree to work towards a mutual goal.
Now it is just AI, executives and shareholders.
This is just the tip of the iceberg
though. Companies are trying to
replace workers everywhere, and one
of the big ones is customer support.
But, in a lot of ways, it’s
backfiring, in some pretty funny ways.
To learn how, watch this video next.